A Guide to the Henkel Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8653-h
Henkel Family Papers 1792-1915
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8653-h
135 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Henkel Papers were purchased on June 15, 1981.
Scope and Content
Additional papers of the Henkel family of New Market, Virginia, and the Tennessee Synod of the Lutheran Church, 1792-1915, and undated, 135 items (1 Hollinger box), including manuscripts, essays, sermons, correspondence, hymns, church records and reports, receipts, and genealogical notes.
Items pertaining to the history of the Henkel Press include:
Verrichtung Der Special-Conferenz Der Evang. Luth. Prediger Im Staat Virginien Gehalten in Rockingham County in Der Neuen Roderskirche Den 6 October 1806
which is the first publication of the Henkel Press and the first major effort by a German printer in Virginia
Kirchliches Jahrbuch
(1829)
David Henkel Against the Unitarians
(1830), appearing as a series of letters from David Henkel and written on rice paper; the index and preface, written by Charles Henkel, for the
Church Hymn Book
(1838); an incomplete sermon book and a smaller sermon book both believed to be in the hand of [ Paul Henkel]; an essay written by Moses Henkel, "A Dialogue Between Mr. Hard and Mr. Soft"; and a translation of John Heubner's
Bible History
.
Material concerning the history of the Tennessee Synod of the Lutheran Church include: "Abstract of the Official Report of a Synodical Meeting Held in Hanover County"; "Action of the Delegates of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod. .."; Church Statistics; "Ecclesiastical Annals and Evangelical Fragments -Report of the Transactions of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod, " including a treatise on regeneration; Notes and Report on Synodical Matters relating to North Carolina and Virginia, including a draft authorizing David Henkel to compile a hymn book; Papers re the history of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod; Reports of the Tennessee Synod Meetings; and the related item, the "Proclamation addressed to the North Carolina Synod Meeting."
Other manuscripts include "Admonitions for Youngsters," "Concerning the Current Custom," and "Should so-called Union Sunday Schools be organized in country school houses."
Genealogical papers include a biographical sketch of [Solbiger] Henkel, genealogical notes, and the record of the family of Gerhard Henkel. Other religious papers include biblical and doctrinal expositions and miscellaneous hymns.
The correspondence, chiefly in German, contains letters from ministers of the Tennessee Synod from areas of Georgia, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Western Virginia. Also present are numerous petitions both in English and German from congregations in remote areas of North Carolina and Tennessee requesting a visiting pastor or permanent minister to come to their churches.
A letter from Ephraim R. Conrad of Missouri to Ambrose Henkel, 1835 June 28, outlines a proposal to establish a Missouri Synod of the Lutheran Church. Other correspondents include: William R. Almond, Adam Bach, P. Barringer, Christian Ludwig [Benzun], Henry Billing, W. Bonham, John Bottler, the Rev. Ephraim Conrad, the Rev. John Grob, Paul Henkel, Philip Henkel, [Gideon] Henkel, Jacob Housk, Phillip Housk, Adam S. Link, Adam Miller, Daniel Moser, George A. Printz, [Mary] Rinehardt, Henry Rupert, G. Shober, Henry Wetzel, and John Youngman.
Container List
- The Henkel Papers
  - "Abstract of the Official Report of a Synodical Meeting Held in Hanover County", 1832
  - "Action of the Delegates of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod...in regard to the organization of a more general union among the Evangelical Lutheran Synod in the South", 1886 Jun
  - "Admonitions for Youngsters", n.d.
  - Bible History translated from John Heubner's work, n.d.
  - Biblical and Doctrinal Expositions
  - Biographical Sketch of Solbiger Hinkel, son of Jacob & Barbara Hinkel, 1792 Feb 11
  - Church Statistics, n.d.
  - "Concerning the Current Custom," with untitled verse on verso, n.d.
  - Correspondence, 1801-1847, 1906, n.d.; (2 folders)
  - "A Dialogue Between Mr. Hard and Mr. Soft" by Moses Henkel
  - "Ecclesiastical Annals and Evangelical Fragments" - Report of the Transactions of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod, including a treatise on regeneration, 1829
  - Genealogical Notes, n.d.
  - Hymns, n.d.
  - Index to a Church Hymnal Book by [Paul Henkel ?], [1838]
  - Kirchliches Jahrbuck recorded by Ambrose Henkel, 1829
  - Miscellaneous Papers, n.d.
  - Notes & Report on Synodical Matters relating to North Carolina and Virginia, including a draft authorizing David Henkel to compile a hymn book
  - Papers re the history of the Evangelical Lutheran Tennessee Synod and related papers, 1822-1915, n.d.
  - Preface to a Church Hymn Book by Paul Henkel, written by Charles Henkel, 1838 Aug
  - "Proclamation addressed to the North Carolina Synod Meeting", 1822
  - Record of the family of the Rev. Gerhard Henkel and his descendants, 1843 Dec
  - Receipts and Other Business Papers, 1809-1846
  - Reports of the Tennessee Synod Meetings, 1829
  - Sermon Book, n.d.
  - Sermon Book belonging to [Paul Henkel ?], incomplete, n.d.
  - "Should so-called Union Sunday Schools be organized in country school houses?" by Elon O. Henkel
  - Verrichtung der Special-Conferenz der Evang. Luth. Prediger Im Staat Virginien, 1806 Oct 6
- OVERSIZE FOLDER
  - "David Henkel Against the Unitarians", 1830